## **Bastian Gruber**

Professional Code

LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/bastiangruber GitHub: github.com/gruberb

Project: rustwebdevelopment.com E-Mail: gruberbastian@me.com

## **SUMMARY**

Passionate Software Engineer and published Author ("Rust Web Development" - Manning). I have over 10 years of experience working in many roles (Tech Lead, Customer Facing, Systems Engineer, Frontend and Backend), in multiple companies (StartUps with 3-8 people, small businesses with around 50 people and large scale enterprise from 200 to 5.000 people). I organize community events (Rust and Tell Berlin, besides others). I am considered a great team player, and lover of software.

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Systems Engineer - Full-time

April 2023 - now

Toposware, Remote

Developing a Peer-to-Peer distributed network, with high throughput and low latency. Developing the protocol and the services in-house.

- Working in a small, tight group of engineers
- Writing specifications and RFCs
- Implementing the p2p protocol on top of libp2p in Rust
- Ten-folding the throughput from the initial implementation
- Project management, Pull Requests and Issues are all open source
- Setting up GitHub CI/CD pipelines

Senior Software Engineer - Full-time

August 2022 - February 2023

Centrifuge, Remote

Centrifuge works on equalising access to financial products. We create the opportunity to move pooling of funds for loans away from banks-only, and give the chance for small business to apply for loans through our protocol, and for more than one investor to invest in these loans. We use the Polkadot ecosystem to build our product as a base layer.

- Working in a self-managed organisation wearing different heads (Head of Documentation, Protocol Engineer)
- Writing specifications and RFCs
- Implemented the Centrifuge protocol with Rust
- Building out a runtime on top of Substrate
- Project management, Pull Requests and Issues were all open source
- Setting up GitHub CI/CD pipelines

Sr. Solutions Architect (Professional Services) - Full-time

June 2020 - August 2022

Twilio Inc., Remote

Twilio just started to create their Professional Services team in EMEA and I was the second SA joining their team. The goal is to support and enable small to large scale customers using the Twilio APIs, help them integrate the services, do code reviews and review their architecture.

- Acted as the Technical Lead inside Fortune 500 companies
- Involved in hiring and onboarding
- Creating architectural specifications
- Develop reusable deliverables for customers
- Leading customers through a technical solution
- Code reviews

• Setting up sales and feedback cycles

Author of "Rust Web Development"

October 2020 - December 2022

Manning Publications, Remote

Writing the book "Rust Web Development". Research, writing and marketing the book in partnership with Manning.

- Selling 3k copies in the first 12 months
- Interviewed by 5 podcasts
- Teaching concepts from what a runtime is to how to deploy an efficient Rust code base
- Copy editing and marketing through different channels
- Held a Reddit AMA to answer questions from readers and Rustaceans

Systems Engineer - Contract

September 2019 - May 2020

Kraken Digital Currency Exchange, Remote (San Francisco)

Part of the first Rust team of the company, replacing the core trading engine with Rust. Worked alongside 12 highly experienced Software Developers from all over the world. Refactor code from PHP to Rust, wrote new features in Rust in a well-tested highly secure manner.

- Re-wrote several PHP services in Rust to increase the throughput 100fold
- Wrote new services in Rust from the ground up
- Cross-communication with different teams and the CTO

Software Engineer, Tech Lead Scholarship, Enterprise, StartUp September 2010 – August 2019

- Was the first employee in two companies, setting up infrastructure, processes and the tech stack
- Worked both as a freelance consultant and full time employee
- Guided teams through learning a new language and maintaining a new technology stack
- Integrated security related infrastructure for IoT companies
- Mentored and guided junior developers

## **EDUCATION**

Bachelor of Science, Computer Science

September 2010 - February 2014

TH Ingolstadt

Scholarship from Allianz Deutschland AG to study Computer Science, fully funded and with trainings in Scrum, Java, PL/I and mainframe systems on the side.